John Ruskin: Letters to Thomas Goff Lupton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Dated letters, Series I
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1858 December 4; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink. Housed with one undated ALS. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Ruskin writes that he will send Lupton two plates on Monday afternoon, unless it rains. He asks Lupton to be at home to receive them and to bite them as quickly as possible. Ruskin specifies that he would like the plates to be bitten according to his drawings, and would rather have the piece be too light than too dark. He refers to an image of Bolton rocks to be used as a guide, and gives Lupton further instructions about the care necessary in biting the plate.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1858 December 4?]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink. Housed with ALS dated 1858 Dec 4. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Ruskin writes in an anxious tone, saying, "Now mind, if you overbite this, you will ruin me, for a fortnight at least, for I am tired and couldn't set about another etching directly..." Ruskin confesses that he is nervous about Lupton's work, as he feels that Lupton has ignored his instructions and made the plate "twice as dark" as he has requested. He gloomily predicts that if Lupton makes the same mistake, "it is all up with it." Ruskin repeats his instructions about the handling of the plate, and asks Lupton to then send it to Mr Brookes and to send him fifty-two proofs. He needles Lupton to hurry his work, reminding him: "I am anxious about it." Ruskin closes with further specifics and a note that he is sending (or has sent with this letter) a proof for Lupton's review.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1860 January 11; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 20 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown ink. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Written on pale blue ruled paper. Envelope bears Ruskin's red wax seal. Ruskin asks Lupton to engrave "a couple of mezzotints for me for this last volume." He inquires whether such a task would be possible in the next few months, and chides Lupton for not sending word of how he is doing. Ruskin asks whether Lupton can have "what you can spare of my libers [?] packed" when he receives Ruskin's next parcel, so that the bearer can pick them up. On verso of this letter is a message which appears to be from Lupton, in response to Ruskin's. Lupton replies to the bearer's verbal message about Ruskin's note, saying that he will do anything he can for the next volume. The message appears to be cut off, with the note paper torn below a portion of Lupton's writing.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1861 October 30; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 27 x 22 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Written on pale blue ruled paper, folded and sealed without envelope. Ruskin writes from Lucerne, Switzerland, addressing Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin asks Lupton what he thinks of him at this point in time, after an apparently lengthy silence in their correspondence. Ruskin explains that he has "been so ill all this year that I felt I must rest altogether," and says that he has "not written a business note nor thought a business thought," for several months. Ruskin writes that he feels better, and does not expect to "get off the rails anymore." He notes that he will be in town at Christmastime, and will visit Lupton soon thereafter, making plans for them to finish "the two brownies" (perhaps mezzotints?) then. Ruskin asks Lupton to send him a line at Lucerne, to let him know how he is doing. He tells Lupton that he can also send it "care of Mr Allen at Denmark Hill & it will come all right." Ruskin closes warmly, "ever affectionately yours, J Ruskin."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1863 July 31; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 25 x 20 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Written on lightweight pale blue paper and addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes to Lupton that "in case I should not be able to come & see you before I or you leave town could you kindly put up for me the three steel plates of the lake, dog, and castle." He remarks that the "total loss" of a plate depicting a Venetian arch (accompanied by a pen and ink sketch of the plate), is "very provoking." Ruskin notes that he has been "over all the rubbish" and does not believe the plate is in his house. He closes warmly, "ever affectionately yours, J Ruskin."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1863 August 3; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Ruskin writes to say that he is glad that Lupton is well and enjoying two "beautiful subjects." He says that he will send for the plates the next day. He writes that he will be going into the country for ten days, where he can be reached at "Sir Walter Trevelyan's in Wallington, Newcastle On Tyne." He tells Lupton that if he would like to send him a proof there, "it is just the place to compare it with nature in." Ruskin thanks Lupton for his good wishes, but says that he does not expect ever to regain his health, "and for happiness--none but in giving up all my art plans and work and setting myself to [see]...what a simple life of voluntary poverty can do for the involuntarily poor." Ruskin complains of "these accursed days of cruelty and war," saying that they prevent him from feeling at peace.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1868 April 2; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown ink. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Sent to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes Lupton that he became ill on the day that Lupton sent him a plate. He writes to say that he is "up again, after physicking & some fever, & lemonade & bad nights." He writes that he will be back to work.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1868 April 2; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown ink. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Letter is sent from Ruskin's home at Denmark Hill. Ruskin writes to Lupton to say that he has "often been thinking of" him, but has had poor health lately. Ruskin elaborates, saying that he has "been in trouble of heart continually increasing, lately,--increasing indeed in the seven last years of my life." Ruskin hints cryptically about "a reason," which he can only reveal when he sees Lupton in person, for his recent decision to retire from "active life," and to "write to no one" for a time. He says that he plans to continue with his own "poor work, about Turner, and leaves & stones, as I used to do." He continues describing his resolution not to write to anyone "for many a day," saying that he has just written to an old friend of Turner's to acknowledge his friendship and trust, but that this will be the last letter he writes for quite a while. Ruskin says that it is "in other hands," to determine how long he must remain in this retirement. He asks Lupton if he will be home to receive him, and closes warmly: "Your affectionate friend, J Ruskin."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1868 April; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 32 x 20 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Letter is written on a large piece of pale blue paper. Envelope has various notes written in pen and ink on it, seemingly from a later date than the letter. Letter conveys Ruskin's corrections/instructions to Lupton based on some proofs that he has seen recently. Ruskin talks about the shading and appearance of shells, asking that Lupton "stop out everything but the insides of the two shells...so as to be safe that the outlines don't get hard..." He includes other notes based on the proofs, explaining that he has marked up the images.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1871 January 5; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Sent from Ruskin's home, Denmark Hill, to Lupton at Russell Square. A warm letter in which Ruskin addresses Lupton as his "dear old friend," and thanks him for a previous letter. Ruskin writes that he will come see Lupton soon, and refers to items presumably sent with the letter as "some things to show you what I'm about..."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1871 Apr [early]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Stationery labeled "Broadlands, Romsey," although preserved with a mismatched envelope stamped "Tunbridge Wells." Envelope also dated May 1855. A rather friendly and not overly serious letter from Ruskin, who writes that he was going to come see Lupton, but doesn't know what his plans will be. He asks what Lupton's plans for being at home will be during the rest of the week (10-16 April 1871). He writes about wanting one of Lupton's "old drawing[s]" of "pigs and wheelbarrow." He remarks that he worries he will have to pay "a year's income to get it." Ruskin also writes that he is "more a fool than ever--and you know how much that is saying." Overall, the letter is warm and fairly jovial, very different in tone from Ruskin's professional communications.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1871 April 11; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Sent to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes to Lupton about an engraving of "Chamonix," and asks if it can be sent "off today--if you can find something for him to pack it nicely in." He also refers to "seaweed plates from Brookes" and asks Lupton to makes some corrections as marked with x's (on a proof or other sheet presumably included with this letter). Ruskin includes a rough sketch of the amendment that he wants Lupton to make.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1871 December 16; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Written on plain letter paper but with a black-bordered mourning stationery envelope (Ruskin's mother died in 1871). Ruskin writes that he is "in great indignation of what you tell me and will do all I can to [put] the lithographs down." He says that he is glad that Lupton has been out of town, and then remarks that "nothing can come of" certain lithographs on "absurdities" and for Lupton not to worry about them.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1871 December 16; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Written on black-bordered mourning stationery. Ruskin's message has a somewhat feeble and depressed tone. He thanks Lupton for a "kind little note" received previously, and seems to apologize for not coming to see him in person because "this year has been a hard and bad one for me." He closes warmly, saying that he is nevertheless always "Affectionately Yours, J Ruskin."
  - Letter to Thomas Lupton, Jr., 1873 May 26; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Letter is addressed from Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire. Ruskin had purchased Brantwood in 1871 and made it one of his primary residences in 1872. This letter is written in a hand that does not appear to be Ruskin's, indicating that he was somehow unable to write it himself and likely dictated it to another person. The message is one of condolence, addressed to Thomas Lupton's son, offering sympathy upon news of Lupton's death. Ruskin expresses deep sorrow, praising Lupton's knowledge and remarking that he had "no more esteemed--and scarcely a more regarded, friend" than Lupton. Ruskin closes by saying that he knows he cannot offer any way to alleviate the family's sadness.
- Undated letters, Series II
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1851-1856]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Ruskin remarks that he is pleased that Lupton likes a recent etching, but that "we must do better, some day..." He asks Lupton to give orders about lettering for a flyleaf, saying that he should "match the lettering enclosed of the companion etching and get it...to Brookes's hands for working off as soon as may be." Ruskin notes that he will soon "choose a brown for your plate--Bolton," and that if Lupton does not like his choice, he can have half of the run made in some other shade; this way, Ruskin writes, the public will be able to "have different colors."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1850s]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Street. Letter is dated only "Dec 6" and seems to be a series of notes for Lupton about the etchings. Ruskin asks him to "try to get the gradation of the dark blue part of water into lighter part..." and remarks that he thinks Lupton's "grounds are too fine...[and] block up the etching like so much Roman cement." He follows this with more comments and instructions. He says that the Bolton image is overbitten, but admits that it is his fault, for "taking too much pains the other night." This may possibly be a fragment of a longer letter, or may be done in a somewhat informal style.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1850s]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Ruskin writes to Lupton asking if he can send back the plates and etchings for "Mill at Chartreuse, [this title is struck out]" "Ben Arthur," and "Valley of Chamonix." He remarks, "I shall have such a puzzler for you," stating that the next plate (name is illegible) has driven him "half mad".
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1850s]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Ruskin writes that he is relieved "in mind" by Lupton's recent note, after having feared that the engraver had "gone to Skiddaw." He refers to a drawing that was apparently sent with this letter (not via post), and asks Lupton to give him an opinion on how much etching would be required in order to mezzotint the image. He follows with specific questions about what to do with the etching, commenting that he "cannot get the effect of the pines, or glacier..." He asks Lupton to please send the drawing back when the etching is done, and tells him that Boys will "put it on steel for you." He closes with an impatient note about the time involved in etching an image of a cathedral, saying that he cannot spend too long on it as he has "more important subjects."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1851-1860]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. Housed with other ALS ca. 1851-60, which describes Ruskin's "horror" at delays in work with preparing plates "Crest of La Cote" and "Crests of La Cote and Taconay." (Box 1, Folder 56)
    This letter is addressed to Thomas Lupton's son Nevil, who may possibly have helped Lupton with some portion of his work for Ruskin. Ruskin writes asking for a ground to be laid on a plate, "left for directions by your father." He says that he would like the plate ready as soon as possible, as he will be in Keppel Street the next day and will bring his tools.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1851-1860]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen abd black ink. Housed with ALS from Ruskin to Nevil Lupton, ca. 1851-60. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Ruskin writes Lupton in a panicked and frustrated state, saying that he is "in a state of the greatest possible horror." He describes a potential delay with an item and declares that he cannot possibly wait any longer. Ruskin remarks that he has contacted Brookes "a week ago...& now you write as if nothing was done." He asks Lupton to be at home the next day so that they can speak in person. Ruskin follows with instruction for the "meantime," asking Lupton to tell Brookes to go on with the piece "Crest of La Cote," (published in volume four of Modern Painters), as well as "Crests of La Cote and Tocaonay," and to have a proof of "Bolton" ready in time for his visit the next day. The mention of these particular pieces likely date the letter to the late 1850s.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [late 1850s]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Referring to the plate they are working on, Ruskin asks Lupton to "bite the tinting on the shells with extreme delicacy..." He asks for four proofs of the plate, after Lupton has worked on it, and tells him to keep the plate "for further directions." Ruskin writes: "I send you Rizpah," which likely connects this letter to the late 1850s, the time during which he was writing the fifth volume of Modern Painters, part of which discusses this Turner painting. Ruskin mentions three other pieces, "Source of Arve_on," "Aesaeus & Hesperi[e/a]," and "Cephalus & Procris," which he offers to lend Lupton for as long as he needs them, saying, "I shall make you pay me five pounds each so you may insure if you like."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [late 1850s]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (written on envelope). 8 x 12 cm. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    A brief note from Ruskin asking Lupton to please send him his box so that he can send plates to be bitten for "experiment for fifth volume," (presumably of Modern Painters).
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1851-1865]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Sent to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes that he is obliged to "Mr Cousins' kindness: and yours in managing the matter for me." He asks Lupton to bring Mr. Cousins and a Mr. Witherington "to see the Turner whenever you and they can come..." Ruskin is likely referring to Samuel Cousins, an engraver, and W.F. Witherington, a landscape painter, both of whom were Royal Academicians. He specifies that Lupton should not bring the two other men until after half past one, as he "can't come out of my den till then." He offers lunch to the group if Lupton can let him know of their intended visit. Ruskin discusses the market value of Turner sketches. He then turns to some technicalities about differences between drawings and etchings, saying that he is pleased that Lupton likes his etching so much. He asks Lupton to have fifty impressions made, in "the brown ink, which I like very much," with the plate sent to Mr Armytage for lettering.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1845-1873]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope made from folded paper leaf. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Dated "27th December." Ruskin remarks that his friend, "Mr Tyrwhitt of Christchurch, Oxford, is one of my best helpers in all projects relating to the diffusion of art feeling among the young men at this university..." He describes Tyrwhitt's desire to learn how to mezzotint, and asks Lupton to give him a few lessons. Ruskin acknowledges that he is "asking what is out of your way," but he notes that it is certainly uncommon for "Tutors of Oxford should wish to learn the severe work of art." He closes, "Always affectionately yours, J Ruskin."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1845-1873]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 61)
    A brief message from Ruskin asking Lupton to send him back his box so he can send Lupton another plate in it. He also asks Lupton to order "another steal of same size" and says that he will send the "tracing to be rolled off on it speedily."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1845-1873]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 62)
    A brief note addressed to Lupton with a note on the envelope reading: "There's something wrong with the ground--it's spotty." The note appears to have been carried to Lupton along with other materials. Ruskin requests Lupton to have two plates ready, with etching grounds. He specifies that one of them should have as much steel "as you like to mezzotint on."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1845-1873]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Ruskin dates this letter "Feb 9" but there is no indication of the year (envelope appears to have been carried to Lupton, rather than sent by post). Ruskin writes that he has tried to save Lupton time by putting more work on a plate, and by specifically "putting some variety and grain into [certain portions] under the mezzotint." He remarks that the plate is still quite "large and delicate," and that it is impossible to simply do coarse work on it. He adds, "Turner would have put none at this distance, except a guiding line here & there--but then, the work you would have had in getting variety would have been enormous, and I want this shading bitten just deep enough to blend in with your mezzotint..." Ruskin continues with instructions to Lupton, and requests a proof "as soon as you can." He advises Lupton to consult the mezzotint when biting the plate because he intends to use this particular image as a mezzotint in the book.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1845-1873]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Ruskin writes that he is sending along with proofs "the steel plate against which please bite up to exactly the same pitch as before..." He refers to a pattern enclosed with the proofs, which were likely carried to Lupton (not sent through the post) with this letter, as the envelope bears no stamps. Ruskin gives Lupton further instructions and then asks him to send the plate back "grounded all over, as I shall want to retouch top subjects."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [circa 1845-1873]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink, with graphite date "March 28" written on last verso. (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Letter is dated "March 28" in graphite on last verso, but there is little indication of the year of this item. Ruskin calls Lupton's attention to the "ingeniously" fastened pasteboard protector on a plate that was presumably carried with this message (not sent by post). He gives Lupton instructions for biting the plate, with very specific details comparing the work to be done with that done on the last plate. Ruskin requests four proofs, and for Lupton to ground the plate for more etching. He declares; "I want to put some subject into the blank spaces," and tells Lupton that afterward, he will "finish all up with a transparent ground..."